<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
    "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY date "June 2005"> 
  <!ENTITY version "0.1.1">
  <!ENTITY application "TFLA-01"> 
]>
<article id="index" lang="en">

  <!-- Header -->
  <articleinfo>
    <title>The Fabulous Logic Analyzer #1</title>

    <pubdate>&date;</pubdate>

    <copyright>
      <year>2005</year>
      <holder>Bernhard Walle</holder>
    </copyright>

    <legalnotice id="legalnotice">
      <para>
        Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document
        under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation License, Version 1.1 or
        any later version published by the Free Software Foundation; with no
        Invariant Sections, with no Front-Cover Texts, and with no Back-Cover
        Texts. The complete license text is available from the <ulink
        type="http" url="http://www.gnu.org/">Free Software Foundation</ulink>.
      </para>
    </legalnotice>

    <!-- <authorgroup> -->
      <author>
        <firstname>Bernhard</firstname>
        <surname>Walle</surname>
        <affiliation>
          <address><email>bernhard@bwalle.de</email></address>
        </affiliation>
      </author>
    <!-- </authorgroup> -->

    <releaseinfo>
      This manual describes version &version; of &application;.
    </releaseinfo>
  </articleinfo>

  <sect1 id="intro">
    <title>Introduction to &application;</title>

    <sect2>
      <title>What is this logic analyzer?</title>

      <para>
        A logic analyzer is a device which can monitor the high and low states of several
        input lines of a digital logic. It is useful for debugging digital circuits such
        as bus transfers, etc. You can imagine a logic analyzer to be something like
        a digital oscilloscope.
      </para>
      
      <para>
        Normally, a logic analyzer is a external device with a own controller that has a own
        display or is connected to a PC via USB or serial line. The PC or the display then
        shows the data, e. g. some waveforms.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    
    <sect2>
      <title>What's special about TFLA-01</title>
      
      <para>
        This logic analyzer is designed to be cheap, somehing like a logic analyzer for poor
        men, which means not for industrial use but for hobbyists. It simply consits of a
        schematic which is attached to the PCs parallel port. There's no real external device which 
        collects the data: The schematic just protects the parallel port and converts RS232 
        level (+/- 12 V) to 5 V TTL level on two pins configurable with jumpers. 
        The schematic is described later in this manual. The measuring is done by the PC software
        using the parallel port.
      </para>
      
      <para>
        This means that the speed depends on your PCs parallel port and on the operating system.
        The data ist just collected by a user process to be portable against different operating
        system. However, with my Athlon XP 2200 and a extra PCI parallel card I get on Linux
        data rates about 1 MHz which is quite well for I²C, RS-232, SPI and some other stuff.
      </para>
      
      <para>The software has following features:</para>
      
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para> Triggering </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para> Zooming </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para> Two markers for which the (estimated) times are displayed </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para> 
            Application runs completely in userspace, 
            <ulink url="http://cyberelk.net/tim/libieee1284/">libieee1284</ulink> is used 
            for parallel port access. This means that the installation is easy and the system
            stays stable.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      
    </sect2>
    
    <sect2>
      <title>System requirements</title>
      
      <para>
        TFLA-01 is designed to be portable against various operating systems. It is written
        in C++, uses <ulink url="http://www.trolltech.com/products/qt/">Qt</ulink> as
        cross-plattform API mostly for the graphical user interface and 
        <ulink url="http://cyberelk.net/tim/libieee1284/">libieee1284</ulink> to access
        the parallel port. This means that it is possible to run TFLA-01 on following 
        systems:
      </para>
      
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Linux</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Windows with <ulink url="http://www.cygwin.com">Cygwin</ulink></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>OpenBSD (i386 only)</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>FreeBSD /i386</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Solaris/x86</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      
      <para>
        On hardware side, you need a parallel port. Use the port of your mainboard or a 
        additional PCI card. Forget about USB adapters, they are normally designed for 
        printers and for nothing else and if it would work, the speed would be insuitable for
        a logic analyzer. (Of course, USB is faster than a parallel port, but that does nothing
        say about the speed of such adapters.) Therefore, a normal Mac would be insuitable 
        for such a task -- porting TFLA-01 to MacOS should be not the problem here.
      </para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  
  
  <sect1>
    <title>Getting started</title>
    
    <para>
      You should read this section if you would like to install TFLA-01 on your
      system and get it working. Don't ask me any questions per E-Mail if you didn't
      read this chapter of the documentation completely!
    </para>
      
    <sect2>
      <title>Installing the software</title>
      
      <sect3>
        <title>Linux RPM</title>
        
        <para>
          If you have a RPM based Linux distribution which is mostly up to date (which means
          glibc 2.3, <ulink url="http://www.trolltech.com/products/qt/">Qt</ulink> 3.3 and  
          <ulink url="http://cyberelk.net/tim/libieee1284/">libieee1284</ulink> installed), 
          then just running
          
<screen>$ su
# rpm -Uvh tfla-01-&version;-0.i586.rpm</screen>
          
          should do it.
        </para>
        
        <para>
          Start the logic analyzer via command line by running
          
          <screen>$ tfla-01</screen>
          
          or add a shortcut to your desktop's start menu. In <filename>/usr/share/pixmaps</filename>
          you find some icons which you can use for that.
        </para>
        
      </sect3>
      
      <sect3>
        <title>Unix via source code</title>
        
        <para>
          The normal way to install TFLA-01 on Unix is to compile the source code since
          it is impossible for me to provide binaries for all various plattforms. If you've built
          a binary (preferrable a package) for your favourite Unix flavour and you plan to maintain
          it for future TFLA-01 releases, just drop me a note and I'll put a link on the TFLA-01
          homepage or upload the binary. The users will thank you!
        </para>
        
        <para>
          However, compiling TFLA-01 is not difficult since the dependencies are small. 
          Building on Microsoft Windows is different, so this chapter only describes the 
          build procedure on Unix. At first, make sure that you have following software
          installed and that the preconditions are met:
        </para>
        
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <ulink url="http://www.gnu.org/software/gcc">gcc</ulink> or another C++ compiler
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <ulink url="http://www.trolltech.com/products/qt/">Qt</ulink> 3.3 including
              the developement package. Verify this by running <application>qmake</application>
              on command line. Also, you have to set <envar>QTDIR</envar> and
              <envar>QMAKESPEC</envar> environment properly, see the 
              <ulink url="http://www.trolltech.com/products/qt/">Qt</ulink> documentation for
              more information. On my Linux box <envar>QTDIR</envar> is set to
              <filename>/usr/lib/qt3</filename> and <envar>QMAKESPEC</envar> to 
              <literal>/usr/lib/qt3/mkspecs/linux-g++</literal>.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <ulink url="http://cyberelk.net/tim/libieee1284/">libieee1284</ulink> including
              the developement package (which includes the header files).
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      
        <para>
          Just build the software now with
          
<screen>$ qmake PREFIX=/usr tfla-01.pro
$ make
$ lrelease tfla-01.pro
</screen>
  
          The first command creates the <filename>Makefile</filename> from the
          <application>qmake</application> project file using the specified <literal>PREFIX</literal>.
          This specifies the installation location (and nothing more, i. e. the pathname is
          not compiled in the binary). If you don't specify <literal>PREFIX</literal>,
          <filename>/usr/local/</filename> is used as a default value. The second command
          builds the software and the third command compiles the translation files.</para>
          
        <para>
          To install the software, just run
          
<screen>$ qmake PREFIX=/usr tfla-01.pro
$ su
# make install
</screen>
  
          You have to repeat the <application>qmake</application> step because the binary
          doesn't get installed if it is not present while running <application>qmake</application>.
          Don't ask me if this is a bug or a feature, it just is so and it's no real problem
          if you know it. Then get root privilegues and install the software. Yes, that's all.
        </para>
      </sect3>
    
      <sect3>
        <title>Windows</title>
        
        <para>
          Description will follow as soon as binaries are available. You'll have to 
          install a dummy driver which gives the user access to the parallel port. Not very good
          but most other programs use the same.
        </para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>
    
  </sect1>

</article>
<!--
	vim:set ts=2 sw=2 et ai:
-->
